混沌初世，一片黑暗
Male narrator: In the beginning, there was darkness.
接着...爆炸
And then... Bang.
产生了无边无际的时间、空间和物质
Giving birth to an endless expanding
existence of time, space and matter.
有一个地方，每天都有新发现
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking the mysterious,
但它依然极端神秘，让人饶有兴趣
the mind-blowing, the deadly secrets of a place
它就是宇宙
we call the universe.
在这个广袤的太空
Between stars, between galaxies,
大多数星体和星系
in the vast majority of space,
其温度远低于零下450度
the temperature reads more than 450 degrees below zero.
极度严寒的太空甚至让我们呼吸的空气
The deep freeze of space would turn even the air you breathe
变为坚冰
into nothing more than solid ice.
遥远的冰冻世界
Narrator: Now far off frozen places
带来了奇异的新奥秘
bring strange new mysteries.
布莫让星云也叫领结星云，比太空环境寒冷得多
The Boomerang or Bow Tie nebula is actually colder than the surrounding space.
冰冻世界里有生命吗？
Narrator: Is there life on frozen worlds?
而且，极端低温为什么会导致
And why does the ultimate cold
超乎我们认识的物理现象？
change physics as we know it?
我们能让光变慢到自行车那样的速度
We can take light and slow it down to the speed of a bicycle.
让我们一起去寻找宇宙里最低温的地方
Narrator: Join us as we travel in search of the lowest，temperatures in the universe,
那个极端严寒的世界吧
and the ultimate deep freeze.
（英文字幕的制作信息）
Sync and corrections by n17t01 www.addic7ed.com
《宇宙：深度冻结》
要深刻理解宇宙最低温的地方
To appreciate the coldest places in our universe,
就得了解
it's important to remember
它们以前炽热到什么程度
just how hot all of existence once was.
=========纪录片之家倾情奉献=========
========http://www.jlpzj.net========
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
大爆炸剧烈爆发离子和能量
We think of the Big Bang as the ultimate hot event--
是一个极度高温的过程
An excitement of plasma and energy.
在宇宙还处在高温的时候
When the universe was really hot,
它并没有真正成形
it was really without form.
放射物和粒子在高速运动
There was just radiation and particles all zooming around,
相互转变
turning into each other.
大爆炸过程极其高温
The Big Bang was a supremely hot event,
大约是一亿兆兆度的开氏温度
roughly a hundred million trillion trillion Kelvins.
科学家们所说的开氏温度
Narrator: Scientists measure temperature using the Kelvin scale,
其基准是绝对零度
which begins at absolute zero
那是已知的最低温度
-- The coldest cold we know
原子运动此时完全不存在
-- A complete lack of atomic movement.
在地球上...平均温度是开氏288度
On Earth... the average temperature is 288 Kelvins...
即华氏59度...
Or 59 degrees Fahrenheit...
两种表述虽然不同，但都是指同一温度
Two different ways of noting the same temperature.
宇宙形成之初
When our universe first formed,
温度很高，甚至原子都不能存在
it was so hot that not even atoms could exist.
整个宇宙除了单纯的能量，什么都没有
The entire universe was nothing except for pure energy.
在一百秒后
It took a hundred seconds for our universe
宇宙温度降到了十亿度
to cool to the point that it was only a billion degrees.
在很长的时间里，温度仍然很高
For a long time, everything was so hot
一切都被分裂为亚原子微粒
that everything was divided into subatomic particles
不是现在传统的原子状态
-- Not real traditional atoms the way that we think of matter now.
当宇宙温度降至足够低
The universe had to cool down to a sufficiently low temperature
首先是原子核得以形成
that, first of all,atomic nuclei could form,
然后中性原子形成
and then neutral atoms could form.
因此，如果不是宇宙温度降到足够低
So without the universe cooling
down to a sufficiently low temperature,
我们就不会存在
we wouldn't exist.
宇宙温度继续下降，直到大爆炸后的56,000年
The universe kept cooling, until 56,000 years after the big bang
它冷却至9,000度
it had cooled to 9,000 degrees.
在大爆炸380,000年后，则下降至
And the universe kept cooling, until 380,000 years after the Big Bang
大约开氏3,000度
temperatures reached about 3,000 Kelvin.
这是一个拐点，物质与能量终于分开
And that was the point out which matter and energy finally parted company.
正是温度的下降，才让我们能够开始理解
Narrator: As temperatures dropped to a level we can start to comprehend
热量与温度之间的关系
-- It's important to understand the relationship between heat and temperature.
热量是能量转移的量度
Heat is a measurement of energy transfer.
温度是作用力
Temperature is action.
让微粒持续碰撞
One of the easiest ways to think of temperature
是观察温度最简单的方法之一
is as the constant collision of particles.
你增加房间里气体的量
You increase the amount of gas in a room,
它们会开始碰撞--互相紧挨着...
they start colliding-- One particle against another...
就象下午人流高峰期的东京街头
Like people in a busy crosswalk on a Tokyo rush-hour afternoon.
正如这些气体分子相互碰撞，温度会升高一样
As those gas molecules collide one with another, the temperature goes up.
在人碰人时
And as those people collide one with another,
速度被转移，人会趔趄
their velocities get transferred, people get bumped forward,
体温也会升高
their temperature goes up.
如果人少了
Now you start removing people--
碰撞会变得不频繁
Those collisions, they become less frequent.
神经变得不紧张，体温就会下降
Nerves become less frayed-- The temperature drops.
同样地，当你抽走房间里的气体
And in the same way, as you remove gas from a room,
碰撞变得不频繁，气体温度就会降下来
the collisions become less frequent, and it becomes cooler to experience.
人类在建设家园的时候
Narrator: As mankind has spread out over all the lands that make up our home in the universe,
领略到了极寒地区的独特魅力
areas of extreme cold hold a special fascination.
在地球上测到的最低温度
The coldest temperature ever measured on Earth
是在南极洲
was measured in Antarctica,
它超过了零下125度
at over 125 degrees below zero.
这杯饮料里的干冰
Dry ice, like the ice in this drink,
大约是在零下109度时凝结的
freezes out at about 109 degrees below zero.
所以在南极洲，你能找到自然形成的干冰
So you could have naturally occurring dry ice in the conditions found in Antarctica,
因为那里非常冷
it's so cold.
在见识了我们星球最低温的地方后
Narrator: Having found the coldest place on our planet,
我们现在去探寻太阳系最低温的地方
we now journey to the coldest place in our Solar System.
出乎意料的是，我们并不需要去很远
And surprisingly, we don't have to go very far.
事实上，人类曾到过那里
In fact, it's a place where humans have already been.
从已知情况来看，最冷的地方
From what we know today, the coldest place
出乎人们的预料
isn't exactly where you'd expect it.
月球轨道探测器
The Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter
在阳光永远照不到的地方
has detected a temperature of minus 397 degrees fahrenheit
发现其中一处只有华氏-397度
in one of those places where the sun's light never quite reaches.
它就位于月球一座环形山的底部
It's actually in the bottom of a crater of our Earth's own Moon.
当月球环绕地球时，它缓慢地自转
As the Moon goes around the Earth, it slowly rotates.
实际上，每绕地球一次就恰好自转一周
In fact, it rotates exactly once per time around the planet,
所以我们总是看到月球的同一个面
allowing us to always see the same face of the Moon.
在环绕的时候
But as it goes around,
阳光永远不能从北极下落
sunlight is never able to reach down into the northern pole
或是从南极升起
or reach up into the southern pole.
两地的环形山会永恒地呆在阴影里
And craters in those two regions，are able to stay in constant shadow,
因为阳光仅从其边缘一掠而过
because the sunlight simply glances past the edge of the crater,
永远都不会照射进去
but never actually shines inside.
科学家在月球上发现极度严寒的现象后
Narrator: Once scientists discovered the ultra-deep freeze on our own Moon,
他们意识到，另有一个地方
they realized there was another place
即使位于如火的行星，也会同样寒冷
that could be equally cold-- On a planet of fire.
就象月球的那些环形山
The realization that craters
它们会保护冰远离阳光
like those on the Moon could protect ices from sunlight,
我们认识到
made us start to realize that
在任何地方的环形山，几乎都可能找到冰
it's possible to find ices in craters almost anywhere.
水星是最靠近太阳的行星
Mercury is the closest planet to the Sun.
在向阳面，极为高温
And its sunlit side is incredibly hot
温度在零上数百度以上
-- Many hundred of degrees above absolute zero.
但水星的某些部分却是永恒地寒冷
But there's some parts of Mercury that are perpetually cold
几乎是太阳系最冷的地方
-- Among the coldest places in the Solar System.
水星的倾斜
Narrator: It's Mercury's tilt-- Or lack thereof--
保持了两极上环形山的严寒
Which keeps its polar craters in a deep freeze.
行星的倾斜以倾斜度来衡量
The tilt of the planet is called its obliquity.
地球大约倾斜23.5度
Earth is tilted about 23 1/2 degrees.
所以我们的两极每年只有六个月见到阳光
So our poles see sunlight about six months out of the year.
水星的倾斜度几乎为零
On Mercury the obliquity is almost zero.
极地上某些深邃的环形山
So at some deep craters at the poles,
会有永久阴影，终年不见阳光
there are spots that are permanently shadowed and never see sunlight.
虽然在太阳系里，离太阳越远就会越冷
Narrator: Although the Solar System gets colder the further you travel from the Sun,
但外层行星和它们卫星的寒冷
the icy conditions of the outer planets and moons
并不能排除生命存在的可能
do not rule out the possibility of life.
在太阳系外边缘
Out in the outer edges of our Solar System,
有各种各样的冰冻卫星
we see a whole variety of frozen moons orbiting the outer planets.
在木星、土星、天王星和海王星周围
Around Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune
全都是冰冻小世界
are all of these little frozen worlds.
令人吃惊的是，可能，仅仅是可能
And what's amazing is maybe, just maybe,
有一些能支持生命存在
some of them can support life.
科学家已经证实
Scientists have overwhelming evidence
木星的卫星木卫二
to support the notion
that on Jupiter's moon Europa
在其表面冰层下，存在着一个流动的海洋
there is an icy crust overlying
a liquid ocean underneath.
太空生物学公认
A common tenet of astrobiology
有液态水，生命就有可能
-- Where there is liquid water there's the chance for life.
科学家们迫切希望象冰海渔夫一样
Scientists desperately want like ice fishermen
能到冰面上去挖洞，看看能捕捉到什么样的生命
to go and dig a hole in the ice and see
what life we can pull up.
因为它会深藏于木卫二的海洋深处
'Cause it could be that deep in the heart of those oceans of Europa,
就好比地球的海洋深处
just like deep in the heart of the Earth's oceans,
那里的火山不仅养育细菌
there's volcanoes that support not just bacteria
还养育着全体生命群--海藻、海黄瓜
but entire colonies of life-- Seaweed, sea cucumbers.
我们所知道的生命，是能够在木卫二海洋存在的
Life as we know it could exist in the oceans of Europa.
土星有一个卫星，它比较活跃
Narrator: One of Saturn's moons is a bit more active,
不断地向太空喷射冰雪
blasting snow out into space.
土星的恩克拉多斯卫星有冰喷泉
Saturn's moon Enceladus has ice geysers.
科学家们在研究这些冰喷泉的时候
And scientists, in trying to find a mechanism for these geysers,
并没有在其中发现液态水
can find no good mechanism that doesn't involve liquid water.
木卫二间歇泉喷发的冰
Narrator: Ice from the erupting geysers on Enceladus
覆盖着附近卫星，使之反光得更厉害
is coating nearby moons, making them more reflective.
科学家们是如何知道这些冰冻之地
So how did scientists know that frozen places,
例如木卫二和恩克拉多斯，发生地质活动的呢？
such as Europa and Enceladus, were geologically active?
关键之处就在于它们光滑的表面
The key lies in their smooth surfaces.
通过“航行者”航天器近距离拍摄恩克拉多斯
When the Voyager Spacecraft sent back the first up-close images of Saturn's moon Enceladus,
他们在广袤的区域里，并没有看到环形山
they saw huge regions with no craters.
这说明了环形山被覆盖，其外观被改变了
This tells us that whatever craters were there were filled in, they were resurfaced.
这种现象很活跃--它们正在被覆盖
It tells us this is an active object-- Stuff's going on here.
卫星、小行星、行星
The number of craters on a planetary surface,
其环形山的数量，反映了表面形成的时间
moon, asteroid, planet, tells us about the age of that surface.
在木卫四或者月球的表面
On Jupiter's moon Callisto or our own Moon,
有许多环形山，这说明其外表面非常古老
we see a lot of craters telling us we have a very old surface--
正如这里的冰
Just like this ice here.
它明显就是旧冰
This ice is obviously old ice.
有片状的，有雪花状的
It has cuts, it has snow.
显然，它已经有一段时间没被重新修整了
Obviously it has not been resurfaced for some time.
这里有我们要的答案
But there's a solution for that.
=========翻译/时间轴:annwayili=========
（如有不当，请多包涵，不吝指导！谢谢！）
行星科学家口中的“重整”
When planetary scientists talk about resurfacing,
并不是我们通常的概念
this isn't usually what we have in mind.
=========纪录片之家倾情奉献=========
========http://www.jlpzj.net========
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
现在，这台磨冰机走了过去
Right here, we can tell the zamboni has passed
我们会说，路面被重整了
-- We can tell there's been a resurfacing event.
磨冰机走过之处
The zamboni has passed,
雪被清理，划痕被消除
clearing off the snow, eliminating the grooves.
同理，恩克拉多斯和提坦这些土星的卫星
This is just like we see on some of Saturn's moons like Enceladus and Titan,
只有新鲜的冰，看不到环形山
where the fresh ice without craters
说明那是年轻的表面
tells us that we have a young surface.
太阳系的寒冷之地
Narrator: The cold places in the distant Solar System
虽然距离遥远，但科学家们非常感兴趣
are of extreme interest to scientists.
研究这些太阳系的外层天体
Studying these outer bodies in our Solar System
能让我们知道
teaches us about
最早期的太阳系由什么来组成
what the Solar System was composed of in its very initial stages.
冰封的天体意味着
So these icy bodies represent
物质处于太阳系初始时期的原始状态
pristine material that really represents the beginning of our Solar System and the
真实反映出构成太阳系的要素
building blocks out of which our Solar System formed.
三、二、一
Three, two, one.
美国宇航局的“新视野号”已经点火发射
We have ignition, and liftoff of NASA's New Horizons spacecraft
开始了长达十年的旅程，去拜访冥王星
on a decade-long voyage to visit the planet Pluto
然后飞往太空深处
and then beyond.
现在，一个新尝试正在进行
Narrator: Now a new effort is underway
它将更近距离地去观察
to get a closer look at some of the frozen leftovers
被冻结的某些太阳系初期的物质
from our Solar System's formative years.
“新视野”的任务是
The New Horizons mission is
探测太阳系外层边缘
NASA's latest mission to explore the outer edges of the Solar System.
它是目前太阳系里速度最快的物体
It's currently the fastest moving object in the Solar System.
在2015年，它将到达曾被认为是行星的冥王星
And in 2015, it will reach the once-and-former planet Pluto.
而在冥王星之后，又到哪里呢？
Narrator: But after Pluto, where to?
这是一代人难得的一次机会，能够近距离地
It's a once-in-a-generation opportunity to get a close-up
去观察数十亿年前的冰封世界
look at frozen objects dating back billions of years.
唯一的问题是，科学家们还没有为新视野号确定第二个目标
The only problem-- Scientists don't yet have a second target for New Horizons.
而这个史无前例的探测器，正以超过37,000英里的时速
Without one, the probe is speeding at more than 37,000 miles an hour,
奔向冰冷黑暗的太空深处
straight for the icy blackness of deep space.
要想知道我们的太阳和行星怎样形成
Narrator: If you want to know how our Sun and planets formed,
只有在太阳系遥远的极冻之处
you just might find answers in
或许才能寻找到答案
the deep freeze of the distant Solar System.
新视野号的冥王星之旅
The New Horizons mission to Pluto
是想得到冥王星大量的新信息
is expected to provide a wealth of new information about the former planet.
在它与冥王星约会后
But after its rendezvous with Pluto,
我们还能怎样去了解外太空的极冻角落
what else can we learn about the coldest corners of outer space
研究我们来自何处？
and where we came from?
这正是数以千计的科学家
That's where thousands of citizen scientists
努力的方向
across the world are hoping to make a difference
但此举无异于大海捞针
by finding a frozen needle in a haystack.
新视野号的任务
The New Horizons mission's destination
-- 拜访这个从前的行星后 -- 被确定下来了
-- After it visits this once and former planet-- Has yet to be found.
现在，世界各地的科学家
And right now there are scientists around the world
会使用“昴星”、“加-法-夏”这些最大型的望远镜
using some of the largest telescopes-- Subaru, CFHT.
去跟踪预定的太空区域
They're peering into the region of space
希望能发现
where we expect to find the object
沿自身轨道运行
that will have just the right orbit that it will
恰好能与新视野号会面的物体
move itself into the path of the New Horizons mission.
但目前的棘手问题是
Now the catch is we have to find
我们要从数以千万计的照片中
that icy object in the outer Solar System
去寻找外太阳系里的冰冻物体
by flipping through all these thousands, millions of images.
对普罗大众来说，这是一个机遇
Narrator: This is a chance for the general public
能够亲身参与探索太阳系最冷之地
to be part of the exploration of the coldest zone of the Solar System.
在这个事情上，我们需要公众的支持
This is where we need the public's help.
我们需要大家来帮助浏览所有照片
We need everyone with eyes to help us look through all of these images,
努力找到新视野号在访问冥王星后
to try and find that piece of ice
有关冰冻物体的蛛丝马迹
that New Horizons will visit after it visits Pluto.
只要访问网站，浏览照片
Narrator: All it takes is visiting a website and looking at images,
你就可能改变历史的发展方向
and you could change the course of history.
这就是项目的神奇之处
And that's the amazing thing about this project.
这个神秘物体
Narrator: It's expected that this mystery object
无论它是什么，在什么时候能被发现
-- Whatever it is and whenever it's found
它会是相当低温，寒冷至极的
-- will likely be cold-- very cold.
毕竟，柯伊伯带本身就是太阳系
After all, other Kuiper Belt objects are among the coldest places
最寒冷的地方
in our Solar System.
离太阳越远
As you get further and further away from the Sun,
它提供给人类、航天器
its energy is less and less able to
以及一切物体保持暖和的能量就越少
keep humans, to keep spacecraft, to keep anything warm.
温度会下降到大约开氏40度
You're down at temperatures around 40 Kelvin.
在此温度下，氮气会变成固体
These are temperatures when nitrogen becomes a solid,
二氧化碳气体会变成固体
when carbon dioxide becomes a solid,
所有我们所熟知的在我们大气中的气体...
when all the things we're used to thinking of as the gases in the air around us...
都会开始变成硬邦邦的东西
Start to become the ground you walk on.
在冥王星表面
And when we look at Pluto and its surface,
是一个完全冰封的世界
what we're seeing is a completely frozen world
几乎没有阳光照射
that sees so little sunlight
我们通常见到的汹涌河流，或者一杯水
that the things that we're used to-- Rivers flowing, a glass of water to drink
都不会存在，即使是我们呼吸的空气
-- They can't exist, because even the air we breathe
也会冻结成为固体
would freeze out to a solid.
另一个被极寒控制的世界
Narrator: Another world dominated by deep freeze--
是一颗遥远的海王星外天体
A far-off trans-Neptunian object
它被冠以北极冰神之名--赛德娜
named for an arctic ice goddess-- Sedna.
在外太阳系的某些物体，比如赛德娜
Some objects in the outer Solar System, like Sedna,
其轨道非常古怪
have very eccentric orbits,
大部分时间处于太阳系的极寒中
and they spend the bulk of their time in the Solar System's deep freeze.
然而，在处于靠近太阳的一小段轨道时
However, when they come close to the Sun for a short period of their orbit,
时间大约是200年，它们会产生
like 200 years, they actually develop
非常稀疏，非常薄的大气层
a very thin, a very tenuous atmosphere.
当行星远离，这个大气层会沉积回到表面
As the planetoid recedes, that atmosphere collapses back to the surface.
赛德娜与太阳的距离，通常约为海王星的三倍
Sedna is currently about three times Neptune's distance from the Sun.
在最接近太阳的时候，是海王星的2.5倍
And upon closest approach, it's 2 1/2 times Neptune's distance.
当它运行到最远端，大约是海王星相应距离的33倍
Now, when it's farthest away, it's
about 33 times Neptune's distance.
总运行周期约为11,000年
And a total orbital period is about 11,000 years.
所以说，它最近一次接近太阳是在公元前9,000年左右
So the last time it was this close to the Sun was around 9,000 BC.
赛德娜怎么会形成这样古怪的轨道呢？
Narrator: So how did Sedna end up with such a strange orbit?
最初有人认为赛德娜被逐至目前位置
Some people initially thought that Sedna got ejected out to where it is
是因为与海王星的相互作用
by an interaction with Neptune.
但基于赛德娜离太阳最近时的距离
But since the closest Sedna ever gets to the Sun
是海王星的2.5倍，事情未必是这样
is 2 1/2 times Neptune's distance, this may be unlikely.
相反地，可能是一颗路过的星体
Instead, it's possible that a passing star
把赛德娜驱逐出去
actually dislodged Sedna,
让诞生在海王星附近的它，来到了目前地方
from where it formed near Neptune out to where it is right now--
说不定，那是太阳形成之时
Perhaps even one of the stars in the cluster
众多星体中的一个
in which the Sun initially is thought to have formed.
在外太空奥尔特云核心
Sedna may be just the first known object in a whole swarm
星罗棋布的冰冻物体中
of other icy bodies that would be
赛德娜也许是我们了解的第一个
the inner part of this Oort Cloud that we think exists out there.
地球上的冰，我们通常认为
Narrator: When it comes to ice on Earth, we're usually talking about
这是水处于冰冻状态
water in its frozen state.
但在赛德娜这样的极寒地方
But ice in the deep freeze of a place like Sedna
冰不见得一定与水有关
doesn't necessarily refer to water.
大多数人一想到冰，就会想到
When most people think of ice, they think of the stuff
冰箱里的东西
that comes out of their freezer.
但科学家们口中的冰
But when scientists talk of ices,
所指的却是一个化学转变
we're just talking about a chemical transition.
我们考虑的是，怎样让它
We're talking about how you can take
有时是气体，有时是液体
sometimes a gas, sometimes a liquid,
降低它的温度，汲取它的能量
and drop its temperature, leech out the energy,
直到原子规规矩矩后，它变为固体
until the atoms change how they behave and become a solid.
在外太阳系，我们发现氨
In the outer Solar System, we find ammonia
--日常用的清洁剂--
-- Cleaning solution--
被冻结成为固体
Freezes out to a solid.
我们发现甲烷、天然气被冻结成固体
We find methane, natural gas, freezes out to a solid.
干冰--在地球上的实验室也制造--
Dry ice-- Something that we make in labs here on Earth--
在太阳系里充斥着
Our Solar System's completely filled with it.
对科学家来说，冰只是特别状态下的东西
To a scientist, ice is just something that is in a different state,
当你加热它，它轻而易举地变成气体或者液体
that readily, when you add heat,
becomes either a gas or a liquid.
某些冰，比如这块冰结的二氧化碳
Some ices, like this frozen carbon dioxide,
不会象水一样从固体变成液体
don't go from a solid to a liquid, like water.
而是直接变成气体
Instead, they go straight into gas.
这种冰是组成冥王星、厄里斯
This type of ice is the exact same sort of stuff
以及外太阳系其它世界的
that makes up part of the composition of Pluto and Eris,
共同的结构材料
and many of the other outer worlds in our Solar System.
我们所见到的彗星尾巴
When we see a comet, when we see its tail
就是气体
what we're actually seeing is gases
--就象气体从这块干冰逸出一样--
-- Like the gases coming off of this dry ice--
在太阳辐射的作用下，它们在彗星后部不断散发
That are getting streamed out behind the comet by the Sun's radiation.
瞧，很有趣吧
Here on Earth, it's just fun to play with.
我正被无数由水构成的冰块包围着
In this room, I'm surrounded by blocks of water ice.
这种冰在地球上非常普遍
And indeed, water ice is quite common here on Earth,
甚至在太阳系的其它一些地方，比如木卫二，也是如此
and even some other places in the Solar System, like Jupiter's moon Europa.
但在某些地方，则是其它类型的冰
But there are some places that have other kinds of ices.
比如土星的卫星泰坦
Saturn's moon Titan, for example,
其表面是甲烷和乙烷的冰块
has methane and ethane ices on its surface.
所以说，由水形成的冰不是冰的唯一类型
So water ice is not the only kind of ice that there is.
要观察冰的多样化，最适当对象...
Narrator: If you're looking for a variety of ices in one convenient location,
莫过于彗星
check out a comet.
研究彗星的好处是
What's exciting about studying comets
你能观察到组成我们太阳系
is that you're seeing the material out of which our whole Solar System,
包括地球在内的物质
including the Earth, was made
它在太阳系演变早期，一下子被冻结起来了
-- Flash-frozen at an early time in the Solar System's evolution.
许多科学家相信，彗星是地球上广袤海洋的源泉...
Narrator: Many scientists believe comets are responsible for Earth's vast oceans...
无数世纪的彗星撞击，把液态水带到了地球表面
That eons of comet impacts brought liquid water to Earth's surface.
果真如此的话，这些携带水份的彗星或许是
If that's the case, these water-carrying comets are likely responsible
地球上每一个生命的始作俑者
for every living thing on the planet.
哪一个更寒冷呢，彗星还是小行星？
So what's colder-- A comet or an asteroid?
这是来自爱荷华州的特拉维斯，对《询问宇宙》提出的问题
That's what Travis S. of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, wanted to 《ask the universe》
特拉维斯，彗星在穿越太空的大部分旅程中
Travis, comets are actually colder than asteroids
比小行星更为寒冷
over most of their journey through space.
这是因为彗星出自太阳系的极冻之地
And that's because comets start out from the deep freeze of the Solar System.
那里非常寒冷
That's really cold out there.
而小行星总是相当接近太阳
Asteroids are always reasonably close to the Sun,
所以它们普遍比彗星暖和
so they're,in general, warmer than comets.
冰冻的彗星，冰封的小行星...
Narrator: Frozen comets, icy asteroids...
被冰雪覆盖的世界是怎样的情形？
But what about whole worlds covered in ice and snow?
我们寻找的宇宙最冷之地
As we continue our search for the coldest places in the universe,
温度会是多低呢？
how low can we go?
在行星表面冰层下存活的生命
And could life survive under the icy surface of a planet
能否在星体之间漫游？
wandering between the stars?
寒冷在宇宙里扮演着关键角色
Narrator: Cold plays a key role in our universe.
它是保护介质，保护着生命元素
It's a preserving medium-- A protector against
比如氢、氧和碳
the scattering of life-giving elements such as hydrogen,
不会流失
oxygen, and carbon.
宇宙的极寒之地可能藏有
The coldest places in our universe may hold answers
关于人类从哪里来这些根本问题的答案
to fundamental questions about where we came from.
所以，关键是找到一个总处于冰川期的世界
So imagine a world where it's always an ice age.
在科幻小说里，冰冻星球普遍存在，比如霍斯（星球大战）、鲁拉・彭塞（星际旅行）
In science fiction, ice planets are common-- Hoth, Rura Penthe.
还有，谁能忘记《太空堡垒卡拉狄加》？
And who could forget the Gun On Ice Planet Zero?
但事实上，科学事实或许会让科幻小说黯然失色
Narrator: But here, science fiction may be eclipsed by science fact.
研究人员正在寻找酷似霍斯的外星球
Researchers are looking for exoplanets that could really be like Hoth
希望找到《帝国反击战》里
-- The ice world from The Empire Strikes Back--
广袤、遍布岩石、满地白雪的世界
Large, rocky, and snow-covered.
霍斯是拥有充沛水量
Hoth was kind of a realistic depiction of what a planet
但因为远离恒星，水被冻结成冰
might be if it's sufficiently covered with water that's then frozen
这样的行星的真实写照
because it's too far from the star.
宇宙里有这样的行星，它有结冰的海洋
You could have a planet that basically has just a-- a frozen ocean
但没有大片陆地露出来
with no land continents sticking out.
一个完全冰封的行星并不是吹嘘出来的
It turns out that an all-ice planet is not only realistic,
地球就有过数次这样的经历
it's happened to Earth several times in our history.
地球曾经数次被完全冰封
Several occasions the Earth has completely frozen over.
我们称此时的地球为“雪球地球”
We call that phase "snowball Earth."
当时出现冰原大扩展
What happens is that the ice sheet grows.
地球变冷，出现更多的冰
Earth cools-- We get more ice.
发亮的冰反射阳光
Ice is light-- It reflects off sunlight.
地球更冷，冰更多
Earth cools, you get more ice.
于是反射阳光更多，冰就更多，造成急剧冰封
Reflect off more sunlight, more ice, and you get a runaway freeze.
后来情况发生变化，局部地方温暖起来
And then something changed, and good fractions of it warmed up,
冰川发生融化
and the glaciers melted.
你可能会以为
In fact, you might expect that
地球大部分时间都处于冰冻之中
the Earth should be frozen most of the time.
但实际并非如此，这是因为
And the reason it's not is that
厚厚的大气层留住了许多热量
we have a thick atmosphere that retains a lot of the heat.
如果没有大气层，由于地球到太阳非常远
If we didn't have the atmosphere, Earth is at such a great distance from the Sun
水将会被冻结
that, in fact, the water should be frozen.
在2012年，科学家确认的太阳系外行星超过700个
Narrator: By 2012, scientists had identified more than 700 extra solar planets
--每年都能保持这个数量的增长
-- A number that keeps climbing every year.
其中许多是气体巨星，极其类似于木星和土星
Many are gas giants-- Worlds that more closely resemble
但与地球截然不同
Jupiter and Saturn than Earth.
要检测到微弱的冰雪世界很困难
Detecting smaller snowy worlds is a difficult
但并非不可能
but not impossible task.
我们现在的检测方法
Our current detection methods
偏重于发现非常巨大，非常靠近其核心星体的行星
tend to find very large planets very close to their parent stars.
当检测方法再先进一些
As our detection methods grow better,
我们就可能发现更多冰冻星球
we're likely to find more frozen worlds.
有一颗行星，被人们称为
Narrator: One such world-- The planet known as
“OGLE-2005-BLG-390LB”行星
OGLE-2005-BLG-390LB.
人们相信，它的大小是地球的五倍
It's believed to be about five times the Earth's size,
按研究人员的说法
and, according to researchers,
它由与地球相似的岩石和冰构成
could consist of Earthlike rocks and ice.
这个外行星与它的太阳的距离
The distance of this exoplanet from its sun
等于火星到我们太阳的距离，或者稍远一点
is about the same, or may be a little further, than Mars is from our Sun.
如果放在我们太阳系里
So in our Solar System,
它将位于火星和木星之间
it would reside between Mars and Jupiter.
这个外行星的有趣之处，是它的质量
This particular exoplanet is interesting in that
大约是地球的五倍
it has about five times Earth's mass.
因此，它被看作是超级地球
So it's considered a super-Earth
是目前发现的质量最小的外行星之一
-- One of the lower mass exoplanets ever found.
但它的温度可能只比绝对零度多50度
But it's temperature could be only 50 degrees above absolute zero.
所以它应当是一个巨大的、冰封的类地行星
So this would be an icy, large Earthlike planet.
其它类型的黑暗冰冻的外行星
Narrator: Another type of exoplanet that's expected to be dark and freezing--
是流浪行星
Rogue planets.
这些行星，由于这样或那样的原因
These are planets that, for one reason or another,
被它们的太阳系抛弃到
have been hurled from their solar systems
恒星之间冰冻的虚无地带
-- Cast off into the icy
nothingness between stars.
众所周知，行星沿轨道绕恒星运行
As far as we know, planets form orbiting stars.
但它们不会一成不变
They don't have to stay there.
重力的作用
Gravity can actually cause planets
会让行星弹射出它们的太阳系
to get slingshotted out of their solar systems.
最终使得流浪行星不能环绕恒星运行
And this is where you can end up with rogue worlds not orbiting a star,
相反地，要在它们之间漂泊
but instead, traveling between them.
没有恒星提供温暖
Narrator: Without a star to provide warmth,
这些行星可能会处在黑暗、寒冷和荒凉之中
these planets are likely to be dark, cold, and barren.
但是寒冷并不意味着死亡
But cold doesn't mean dead.
许多科学家相信，非常有可能的是
And many scientists believe that it's quite possible
即使是在太空里游荡数十亿年之后
that life could exist under the frozen oceans of a rogue planet,
生命仍存在于流浪行星的冰冻海洋之下
even after a billion years of wandering through space.
当它们远离恒星而去
Once they're far away from the star,
就会被冻结起来，被包裹得很严实
they could freeze out and become quite icy.
人们还猜想
But it's also conjectured that
它们中的某些会保留厚厚的大气层
some of them could retain a thick atmosphere,
从而保留了行星上
which would then keep the heat trapped in,
通过地热和放射性衰退
that's created through geothermal processes
所产生的热量
and radioactive decay within the planet.
所以，不是所有的它们都会表面完全冰封
So not all of them are necessarily completely frozen at their surface.
随着宇宙视野的扩大
Narrator: As our view of the cosmos improves,
我们认定的流浪行星数量不断增加
our estimate of the number of rogue planets keeps climbing.
通过最近的模拟，我们认为
Recent simulation suggests
there may be twice as many
银河系的流浪行星数量是恒星的两倍
rogue planets in the galaxy as there are stars.
假如路过的天体把地球从太阳系抛出去
Narrator: So what would happen if a passing star sent Earth
会发生什么事情呢？
spinning out of our Solar System?
随着整个行星的漂移
As the entire planet goes rogue,
骤然进入寒冷漆黑的太空深处
tumbling out into the cold blackness of deep space,
生命能幸存吗？
would life survive?
果真如此，虽然不是全部能量会快速消散
If that happened, we'd very quickly radiate away
但绝大部分会
not all our energy, but a lot of it.
海洋会冰冻，大气会变成固体
The oceans would freeze, the
atmosphere would become a solid.
我们会被抛弃，可能会死亡
We'd be left，probably dead.
整个世界里只剩下毫无生气的城市
But imagine finding that world later on, intact with its cities.
我们不必担心这样的命运
We don't have to worry about this fate.
但文明的发展很微妙，你永远不知道接下来的事
But a civilization growing up around a binary star -- You never know what could happen.
人类也许不能幸存下来...
Narrator: Humans may not be able to survive...
但在海洋之下，结了冰的水
But under the sea, the way our water freezes
会给予生命一个竞争的机会
would give life a fighting chance.
帮助鱼类安全留在地球的因素之一
One of the things that helps keep fish here on the planet Earth safe
是我们日常的水--氧化氢
is our normal water-- Our H2O water.
当它冰结的时候，会由上向下
When it freezes, it freezes from the top down,
这就能给予鱼类保护，让它能在冰面下游弋
leaving the fish safely protected and swimming beneath the frozen surface.
如果是另一个世界，一个正处于极冻的世界
Now if we go to another world-- One experiencing a deep freeze
这个外行星可能会有氨气海洋或者甲烷湖泊
-- That alien planet might have ammonia oceans or methane lakes.
当这些液体结冰时
And those liquids, as they freeze,
会从底部一直冰结到表面
they freeze from the bottom all the way up to the surface
让这些冰湖里的鱼类无处容身
-- Leaving any fish living in those frozen lakes flapping around on the surface.
这可不是养鱼的好地方
And that's not a good place for a fish to be.
如果地球变成流浪行星
If Earth were to become a rogue planet,
我们会在非常深海的俯冲带，看到生命群体
the life forms we see at the very depths of the ocean in subduction zones,
那里有暖流冒出，使得局部海洋充斥着非常热的水
where these thermal vents are filling the local ocean with very very hot water
生命群会若无其事地存活几百万年，或几十亿年
-- Those life forms would go on like nothing ever happened for millions, maybe billions of years.
所以在一个流浪的冰封行星上，在非常深的地方
So it's very possible that in the very depths of an ice planet
生命的存在非常有可能
that's gone rogue, life could exist.
生命能在流浪行星存在，但不会永远存在
Narrator: Life could exist on a rogue planet, but not forever.
毕竟，太空非常非常寒冷
After all, space is very, very cold,
所以说，得感谢温暖，是它给了地球生命
and life-giving Earth remains, thankfully, warmer.
我们地球靠近太阳
We're close to the Sun.
而宇宙里有代表性的地方，它远离任何星系或恒星
The typical place in the universe, far from any galaxy or star,
其温度只比绝对零度多2.7度
has a temperature of only 2.7 degrees above absolute zero.
这是太空本身的温度
That's the temperature of space itself
--相当低温，极为冰冷
-- Really cold, a really deep freeze.
宇宙间最冷的自然现象是什么呢？
Narrator: So what is the coldest naturally occurring place in the universe?
它能营造非常巨大的寒冷环境
It's a place where a simple principle you can test in your
但其原理很简单，你在家里也能尝试
home has led to a very big chill.
在探索了我们最近邻居的寒冷之后
Narrator: Having explored the role of coldness in our immediate neighborhood,
我们现在去一个更寒冷的地方
we now embark on a journey to even more frigid places.
天文学者最近发现了
Astronomers have recently discovered
他们认为可能是迄今为止最寒冷的类星体
what they think may be the coldest star-like object ever found,
其距离地球仅为40光年
a mere 40 light-years away from Earth.
它是一颗被称为Y型的褐矮星
It's what's called a "Y" class brown dwarf.
按科学家的形容，它的表面
And according to scientists, the temperature on its surface
几乎和春季的白天那么暖和
is about that of a warm spring day.
就在2011年，我们首次发现了这种最冷的Y矮星
Just in 2011, we found the coldest "y" dwarf ever found.
它的温度相当低
And this is an object that's so cool
比人类的体温还要低
that it's actually cooler than you or I, as human beings, are.
其温度刚好是华氏80度
And this is an object that's just 80 degrees fahrenheit.
我们太阳的温度为华氏10,000度
Our Sun, by comparison, registers at a toasty
比它温暖得多了
10,000 degrees fahrenheit.
因此，这颗褐矮星是恒星吗？或者不是？
So is this brown dwarf a star, or not a star?
褐矮星是介于行星和成熟恒星之间的天体
A brown dwarf is sort of intermediate between a planet and a full-fledged star.
比起木星般大小的行星，它的质量要大得多
It's more massive than even a Jupiter-sized planet.
但它的质量不足以
But it's not massive enough to ever have
在核心产生持续的原子核聚变
had sustained nuclear fusion in its core.
真正的恒星，其原子核聚变会持续很长很长时间
So a true star has nuclear fusion going on for a long, long time.
而褐矮星只有短暂的原子核聚变
A brown dwarf has nuclear fusion for just a short time.
褐矮星填补了我们所说的
What brown dwarfs do is they bridge the gap between
行星和恒星之间的断层
what we call planets and what we call stars.
褐矮星的冷，不只是因为自身冷
So brown dwarf are cool, not only because they are cold, but
还因为它们有大量的奇异物质
because they have a lot of exotic stuff going on in them.
这些类似恒星的天体，温度相当低
Because they have such low temperatures, you can actually get clouds
所以在外层大气里有云团
in the outer atmospheres of these almost-stars.
那些会是冰云团
And these can be either icy clouds or,
在某些个案中，甚至会是铁云团
in some cases, they can be even iron clouds.
所以我们认为某些褐矮星可能存在着铁雨
So we think that some brown dwarfs actually might have iron rain
铁质被凝结到外大气层
-- Where iron condenses out of the atmosphere
然后象下雨般落到低层
and rains down into the lower layers.
但即使是非常寒冷，还是
But even with the coolest kinds, you can get ices much like the
会有仿似木星云斑一样的冰
ones that we see in the cloudy bands that are on Jupiter,
存在于这些既类似恒星又类似行星的天体上
in these almost-stars but almost-planets.
让我们继续向外太空进发
Narrator: As we continue to move out into the universe,
假如我们突然间来到离地球400光年的地方...
we get about 400 light-years away from Earth when suddenly...
群星闪烁，温度下降
Stars appear to wink out of existence, the temperature drops,
我们会与黑漆漆的“巴纳德68”相遇
and we encounter the inky blackness called "Barnard 68."
巴纳德68很奇特，因为你看不到它
"Barnard 68" is significant because of what you don't see.
它是一团黑块
It's just a black patch.
没有光从那里发出来，也没有光穿越它
There's no light coming from it, there's no light coming through it.
它是天空里既黑漆漆又不透明的地方
It is a black opaque spot on the sky.
这种物体，让人以为是天幕上的小洞
Narrator: What was once thought of as a hole in the sky
如今被称为暗分子云
is now known as a dark molecular cloud.
暗分子云是太空里的巨大云团
Dark molecular clouds are huge clouds in space,
它由气体和尘埃组成
of gas and dust, and when we say "dust"
“尘埃”是指小颗粒的水和硅酸盐
we mean little chunks of water and silicates
并不是清扫厨房时的东西
not unlike you would sweep off your countertop.
阳光和星光
Sunlight, starlight, is only able to
只能穿透气体云团最外面的区域
penetrate the outermost regions of the gas cloud.
当你逐渐深入内部
As you move deeper and deeper within,
这个不透明系统会阻挡所有可见光的波长
this opaque system blocks all the visible wavelengths of light.
只有红外线能够畅通无阻地
Only the infrared light is able to make it
进入到云团深处
all the way into the depths of the cloud.
这就保证了云团不会变热
And this protects the cloud from heating up and,
从而使这些云团内部
in fact, makes the inside of these clouds
成为宇宙间最阴森和最寒冷的地方
one of the most shadowed places and one of the coolest places in the universe.
“巴纳德68”不仅外围冷达开氏16度
Not only is "Barnard 68" a nippy 16 kelvins at its periphery,
当你越深入，还会更冷
as you work your way in, it actually gets colder.
这是一个寒冷的云团
This is one cold cloud.
“巴纳德68”这样的物体，最神奇的地方之一
One of the most amazing things about objects like "Barnard 68"
是它们位于目前宇宙最冷物体的行列
is that right now they're some of the coldest things in the universe.
但自身物质会让它们霍然崩塌，并触发恒星的形成
But all it takes is a shockwave to collapse them down and trigger star formation.
在恒星--最巨型的恒星--最早形成时
And the first stars to form--The largest stars to form--
它们就成为了宇宙间最炽热的物体之一
Are some of the hottest things in the universe.
所以说，某一个暗分子云会在某一瞬间成为
So in one instant, one of these dark molecular clouds
当前环境中最炽热的物体
can become the hottest thing around.
但在这一瞬间之前，却是宇宙里最寒冷的
But the moment before, they were the coolest things in the universe.
让我们继续行程...
Narrator: Continue our trip...
这次我们来到目前宇宙里已知的最冷地方
And we've arrived at the coldest place we know of in the universe
这里距离地球大约5,000光年
-- Approximately 5,000 light-years away from Earth.
我们现在进入了布莫让星云
We are now entering the Boomerang nebula.
这个领结形状的星云
This bow-tie shaped nebula
比宇宙里其它地方都要冷
is actually colder than the restof the universe.
它因为向外喷溅
It's been chilled by the outflow of gas
接近于华氏-458度的气体而变冷
to approximately negative 458 degrees fahrenheit
温度只比绝对零度高1度
-- Just one degree above absolute zero.
布莫让星云
The Boomerang nebula consists of
由濒死恒星快速扩散出来的气体组成
rapidly expanding gases from a dying star.
这些气体的扩散速度非常快
And those gases expand so quickly,
使得它们变冷，其温度低于周围太空环境的温度
that they've cooled to a temperature below that of the surrounding space.
它能达到极端低温，部分原因在于
And part of the reason it's able to achieve its extremely low temperature
它是由扩散气体所组成的
is simply because it's made of expanding gas.
这些扩散气体，就象...
And expanding gas, just like...
这个罐里的一样...
The expanding gas in this can...
气体扩散时，体积变大，温度就会下降
Drops in temperature as the gas spreads out over a larger volume.
说起来，我能让这些每天都喝的水...
In fact, I'm able to take this everyday drinking water...
水现在是室温...
This room temperature drinking water...
我将用罐里的气体让它结冰
And freeze it with the gas coming out of this can.
=========翻译/时间轴:annwayili=========
（如有不当，请多包涵，不吝指导！谢谢！）
我不是说，布莫让星云会有冰
Now I'm not going to claim that the Boomerang has ice,
但你应该明白了，少许扩散气体就能够引发严寒
but you can see that a little expanding gas can create one heck of a deep freeze.
利用现代技术
Narrator: Using modern technology,
我们能够在实验室里得到更低的温度
it is possible to create even lower temperatures in a lab.
所以宇宙间真正低温的地方，或许...
So the true coldest place in the universe may be
就在地球这里
right here on planet Earth.
在实验室里
Narrator: In laboratory experiments,
我们现在能够达到非常低的温度
we can reach very low temperatures now.
最低曾达到1/2纳度
In fact, the lowest temperature ever reached
1纳度就是十亿分之一的开氏温度
is something like 1/2 of a nanokelvin -- A billionth of a degree.
这真的很低了
That's really low.
当温度降到接近绝对零度
Narrator: As the temperature in these experiments approaches absolute zero,
在物质身上发生了奇异的事情
weird things start happening to matter.
原子受极度低温的作用，凝聚在一起
Atoms react to the deep freeze by clumping together in
以离奇的方式排列
a bizarre form of matter.
所有原子进入同一种状态
This is where the atoms all go into essentially the same state.
它们的行为表现很类似，甚至是一样的
That is, they behave in a similar way or even the same way.
从而使得物质很奇异
These are weird, weird substances.
超低温物质甚至能使光停下它的脚步
Narrator: Super-cold substances that can even stop light in its tracks.
在最低温的情况下，我们能够让一束光停止
One of the coolest things we can do is actually stop a beam of light.
这好象很疯狂，但我们确是能够获取一束光
I know it sounds insane, but we can take a beam of light
并让它慢下来
and be able to slow it down,
然后操控它去做你想做的事
and then play with it, do whatever you want with it,
然后再把它释放
and then release it again.
你可以让它停下来
One of the things that you can do with that is stop it,
操控它进入电子信号里
turn it into an electrical signal,
然后又释放它，并让它重回到光束内
and then re-release it and turn it back into light.
这非常有趣，它可以在电子学上有各种应用
And this is really interesting, because it has all kinds of practical applications in electronics.
这仅是极度低温如何改变
Narrator: It's just another example of how a really deep freeze
宇宙万物根本特性的另一个例子
seems to transform fundamental properties of the universe.
此外，许多科学家相信宇宙本身
Then again, many scientists believe the universe itself
正处在一个不可更改的根本转变中
is in for one final fundamental transformation
最终进入深冻的状态...
-- To a permanent state of deep freeze...
届时，没有回头路了
From which there is no return.
宇宙难逃一死
Narrator: The universe is doomed.
某些研究所有实体最后阶段的物理学家
That's the belief of a number of
physicists who study potential
对此坚信不疑
endgames for all existence.
所有星体的热量与力量
All of the heat and power that was present at the start of time
会随着时间缓慢地、平静地溜走
is slowly, quietly, slipping away.
宇宙历史的漫长故事
The whole story of the history of the universe
始于巨大能量在大爆炸时的注入
starts from the injection of this enormous amount of energy in the Big Bang,
也将终结于宇宙扩张时的消散
and watching it dissipate as the universe expands.
源自大爆炸的宇宙
Narrator: A universe that begins with a Big Bang,
它的持续扩张，最终将使能量不足
and continues to expand, will eventually have an energy shortage
而这是无法解决的
for which there is no solution.
在某种意义上，宇宙正在缓慢松懈下来
In a sense, the universe is slowly winding down,
就好比上紧发条的玩具
kind of like when you wind up the spring in a wind-up toy
让它运行一段时间
and you let that toy run for a while.
最终，所有能量会消耗殆尽
Eventually all the energy gets used up
--发条上会没有任何能量
-- There's nothing stored in the spring anymore.
你得再次拧紧发条，才能让玩具动起来
And you'd have to wind it up again to get it to do something interesting.
这些玩具拥有一点点能量
These toys have some initial energy.
在短暂运动之后
And as they go through their little motions,
能量被使用，然后消失
you're seeing that energy be used up and dissipated.
最后，这些玩具会停下来
Eventually, these toys will stop.
它们将处在最低能量状态
They'll be in their lowest energy state.
不可能再输出能量
And there'll be no more possible energy output from them.
当所有星体死亡
Well, once all the stars have died
--当所有能量扩散到整个宇宙
-- Once all the energy has spread out uniformly in the universe
--将会没有任何动静
-- Nothing interesting happens.
因为，正如没有拧紧发条的玩具
Because, like the wind-up toy, it's not wound up.
宇宙的发条不再会被拧紧了
The universe isn't wound up anymore.
宇宙本身还在变大，还在扩张
Narrator: But the universe itself is getting larger--Expanding--
却没有新的能量或热量进入系统
And there is no new energy or heat coming into that system.
如果宇宙不停止自身的扩张
If the universe doesn't tear itself apart first,
宇宙会终结为一个极冻的世界
the universe will end as a deep freeze
--寒冷、黑暗而且压抑
-- Cold... dark... and depressing.
太阳们烧光
Narrator: Suns burn out.
行星们被毁灭
Planets are destroyed.
星系碰撞、坍塌、燃烧，然后散架
Galaxies collide, collapse, ignite, then fall apart--
冰块四处飘散
Frozen shells of their former selves.
在几百个数十亿年之后
Over hundreds of billions of years,
宇宙的每一点能量都被利用了
every bit of energy in our universe gets used up
--消失在无限扩张的太空
--Lost to the ever-expanding void
宇宙的熵会达到致命的最大状态
as the entropy of our universe reaches a final fatal maximum state.
最终，它会扩张到极点
Eventually, it will expand to the point
届时将没有热量留在宇宙里
where there will be no heat left in the universe.
这意味着没有化学反应
That means no chemical reactions.
意味着没有生物作用
That means no biological reactions.
你看到的将是
What you will see is
--宇宙的最终阶段看起来什么也没有...
-- The final state of our universe is really just going to look like a whole lot of nothing...
什么也看不到--没有黑洞，没有白矮星
Nothing to see here-- No black holes, no white dwarf stars,
没有中子星
no neutron stars.
即使是质子也没有...
Not even any protons...
什么都没有
Just nothing.
一个非常寒冷、非常黑暗的宇宙
In a very cold, dark universe,
你会说，这会是终极的深冻
you could say that this will be the ultimate deep freeze.
这是必然的吗？
Narrator: But does it have to be that way?
有什么能让宇宙避免最终成为
Is there anything that could prevent our universe
一个冰冻、黑暗的虚空吗？
from ending up as a frozen, dark void?
要避免宇宙的终极死亡
In order to prevent an ultimate death of the universe,
重力--或者其它类似于重力的奇异力量
gravity-- or some attractive force like gravity
--必须把宇宙所有的子民拉扯回来
-- will have to pull back together all the constituents of the universe.
现在的宇宙正在扩张
Right now the universe is expanding.
我们测量到的重力
And the force of gravity as we measure
并不足以把一切拉扯在一起
it isn't enough to pull everything together.
但要知道，我们还不能完全知道所有的作用力
But we recognize that we don't even know all the players at work.
在过去的20年，我们才认识到暗能量
It's only been the last 20 years that we've even known that dark energy
这是一种令人讨厌的力量，它会分散宇宙
-- which is a repulsive force in essence, something that pushes the universe apart
--我们在20年之前甚至不知道它的存在
-- We didn't even know it existed more than about 20 years ago.
有可能在某一天
But it's conceivable that some day,
加速宇宙扩张的暗能量
the dark energy that's accelerating the expansion of the universe
摇身变为重力一样的吸引力
will become gravitationally attractive.
果真如此，而且它是足够的话
If that's the case, and if there's enough of it,
宇宙或会停止它的扩张，再次坍塌
then the universe may halt its expansion and re-collapse.
我们不知道这会否发生，但它可能会发生
We don't know that that will happen, but it might happen.
在那种情况下，宇宙会经历一次非常高温的热死亡
In that case, the universe will experience a really hot heat-death,
所有微粒会骤然进入到其它微粒里面
where all the particles are slamming into all the other particles.
温度很高
High temperatures.
恒星走向毁灭，行星走向毁灭
Stars get destroyed, planets get destroyed.
只剩下一个不同与往的、死气沉沉的宇宙...
You get a different form of a lifeless universe...
一个以高温代替极冻的宇宙
One which is hot instead of in the deep freeze.
但是，它不会形成“遮阳幕”
Narrator: Still, don't break out the sunscreen yet.
我敢打赌，宇宙会最终成为非常低温的极冻世界...
My bet is that the universe will end up in a very low temperature deep freeze...
因为目前的暗能量，看起来或许会
Because it seems that the current dark energy might be the type
继续加速宇宙的扩张，永不停止
that will continue to accelerate the expansion forever.
假如果真如此，宇宙的温度
If that's the case, the temperature of the universe
会反复接近绝对零度这一终极寒冷的温度
will become arbitrarily close to absolute zero-- The ultimate deep freeze.
寒冷是我们宇宙的一个决定性因素
Narrator: Cold is a critical ingredient of our universe.
它是我们所见到的宇宙的必要组成
Cold is essential to having the universe that we see.
因为如果没有寒冷，能量就不会流动
Because without a cold spot, energy doesn't flow.
你需要能量从热流向冷
You need energy to flow from hot to cold.
正是能量的流动
And it is the flow of energy that leads to
才形成现在的宇宙万物，包括我们人类本身
all the structures that we see in the universe, including ourselves.
所以，如果没有能量通过各种可能方式
So we wouldn't be here if energy weren't trying to flow
竭力从热的地方流向宇宙各处
from hot concentrated organized places
我们就不会在这里存在
into the many forms that it can flow into in the universe.
因此，日后感到冬日的寒冷或是被雪球打中的时候
So the next time you feel a winter chill or get hit with a snowball,
你要记住--如果不是寒冷，你就不会在这里
just remember-- If it weren't for cold, you wouldn't be here.
而且，如果算是一丝安慰的话
And if it's any consolation, you won't be around
现在的你不用花上几百个数万亿年
hundreds of trillions of years from now when the universe
去陪同宇宙迎接最后的极冻结局
enters its final state of deep freeze.
（英文字幕的制作信息）
Sync and corrections by n17t01 www.addic7ed.com